<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Performance | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/performance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-22T12:29:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Person’s Bloat…]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/one-persons-bloat-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-25T15:15:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/one-persons-bloat-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure id="fig-2016-10-25-1" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-25/webbloatscore.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-25/webbloatscore.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-25/webbloatscore.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-25/webbloatscore.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""></figure>

<p>The <a href="http://www.webbloatscore.com/">Web Bloat Score Calculator</a> has been making the rounds on Twitter and I wanted to share my immediate thoughts on it.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>First off, I am a big fan of simple tools that provide an often much-needed reality check on a project. Based squarely on its simplicity, I’d put this tool right up there alongside <a href="https://www.webpagetest.org/">WebPageTest</a> and <a href="https://whatdoesmysitecost.com/">What Does My Site Cost?</a>. The Web Bloat Score (or WebBS… clever) Calculator is about as simple an interface as you can get: Enter a URL &amp; hit the “Calculate” button.</p>

<p>When you do this, the service runs two tasks:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Load the URL and all of its assets, calculating a total page weight and chronicling the number of requests required to get there; and</li>
  <li>Generate a static screen capture of the page and then grab its file size.</li>
</ol>

<p>Once it has these two bits of info, it compares the real file size of the tested page against the image version to come up with your WebBS.</p>

<p>I <a href="http://www.webbloatscore.com">ran the calculator against the 10k Apart contest homepage</a> and here are the results:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">URL</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Page Size</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Requests</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Image Size</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">WebBS</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">https://a-k-apart.com/</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">200 <abbr title="kilobytes">kB</abbr></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">49</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">195 <abbr title="kilobytes">kB</abbr></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">1.03</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Not too bad, considering <a href="http://www.webbloatscore.com/Details/612ea9a9-c548-4e20-99d1-910b449ba2c4">the number of images on the page</a> and the interactivity of the SVG. In the documentation about the tool, they have this to say about a high WebBS:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A high WebBS usually indicates unused stuff on the page: JavaScript, CSS, oversized images, etc. Maybe you have a valid reason for that content. But more often than not, it means you can optimize it more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I completely agree with the sentiment here: smaller is better and if there’s a huge discrepancy between the file size of an image of your page and the page itself, there <em>may</em> be something not so awesome going on behind the scenes. They reference Amazon as being particularly bad, with a WebBS of 20 (<a href="http://www.webbloatscore.com/Details/4abea720-677c-48f6-9ff2-2b816424be06">I got 12.3 in my test</a>, but Amazon frequently changes their homepage).</p>

<p>There’s always room for improvement when it comes to optimization, but I also worry about folks getting too hung up on numbers like this, especially striving for a score of 1 or less. Here are a few legitimate reasons your score may be more than 1:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Your page is heavily interactive.</strong> The calculator does not take into account any sort of interactivity—progressively enhanced or not—nor does it tell you how well-optimized your JavaScript code is. There’s also the possibility that you’ve consciously decided to trade verbosity for speed. For large loops, for instance, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duff%27s_device">Duff’s device</a> is much faster but a lot more verbose than a normal <code>for</code> loop.</li>
  <li><strong>Your page serves alternate file formats.</strong> The tool runs <a href="http://slimerjs.org/">SlimerJS</a> to collect the performance data and, for instance, it doesn’t currently support WebP images. We serve WebP with a JPG or PNG fallback on the 10k Apart site (using <code>picture</code>), but <a href="http://www.webbloatscore.com/Details/612ea9a9-c548-4e20-99d1-910b449ba2c4">the file log</a> doesn’t include the WebP images at all.</li>
  <li><strong>You make use of micro-optimizations.</strong> Perhaps you use <a href="https://github.com/filamentgroup/loadCSS"><code>loadCSS</code></a> or <a href="https://github.com/filamentgroup/loadJS"><code>loadJS</code></a> or split your CSS into a default and advanced stylesheet (with the advanced one only loading if media queries are supported). Perhaps you lazy load images or fonts via JavaScript. Perhaps you only load certain assets or scripts based on browser capabilities. The calculator takes none of this into account.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are just three reasons to take your WebBS with a grain of salt. It’s good for a gut-check, but I wouldn’t spend a whole lot of time worrying about getting your score at or below 1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Would You Do With 10kB?]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/what-would-you-do-with-10kb/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-17T14:48:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/what-would-you-do-with-10kb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sixteen years ago, <a href="https://twitter.com/stewart">Stewart Butterfield</a> conceived of a contest that would test the mettle of any web designer: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20000510010054/http:/www.sylloge.com/5k/home.html">The 5k</a>. The idea was that entrants would build <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/5k">an entire site in 5kB of code or less</a>. Its aim was to force us to get creative by putting a bounding box on what we could do:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Between servers and bandwidth, clients and users, HTML and the DOM, browsers and platforms, our conscience and our ego, we’re left in a very small space to find highly optimal solutions. Since the space we have to explore is so small, we have to look harder, get more creative; and that’s what makes it all interesting.</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<p>The 5k contest ran from 2000 until 2002. In 2010, <a href="http://www.zeldman.com/2010/07/29/10k-apart-%E2%80%93%C2%A0inspire-the-web/">An Event Apart and Microsoft revived the idea</a> with an updated limit and a new name: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20100730090946/http:/10k.aneventapart.com/">10k Apart</a>. Staying true to its roots, this new incarnation, which ran for two years, continued to push designers and developers to get creative within a pretty extreme (though slightly expanded) limit while incorporating new goodies like HTML5 and responsive design.</p>

<p>I’m thrilled to announce that <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/">the 10k Apart contest is back</a> and brings with it a handful of new challenges:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Each page must be usable in 10kB or less.</strong> The 10kB limit no longer applies to the size of a ZIP archive of your entry; the 10kB limit now applies to the total initial download size of the baseline experience of each page in your project. When we say “baseline experience,” we’re talking small screen devices running older, less capable browsers. The 10kB limit will apply to every page and whatever assets it loads by default; that means images, CSS, JavaScript, and so on.</li>
  <li><strong>Progressive enhancement is the name of the game.</strong> Your project should start with a super-basic, bare-bones-but-usable experience that will work no matter what (including without JavaScript). You can use clever CSS and JavaScript techniques to enhance that experience as it makes sense to do so. For example: You might lazy load an image using JavaScript if the screen size is above a certain threshold or when certain other conditions are met. Entries that depend entirely on JavaScript to render the front-end won’t be accepted. If you need a primer on progressive enhancement, <a href="http://alistapart.com/search?keywords=progressive%20enhancement">consult the pages of <cite>A List Apart</cite></a>.</li>
  <li><strong>Back ends are in this year.</strong> In previous iterations, each entry comprised client-side code submitted via ZIP file. Over time, that limitation led to an over-reliance on JavaScript for rendering. No more. This year, you can create dynamic experiences that work without front-end JavaScript using Node, PHP, Python or .Net. You will submit your entry as public GitHub repository (so we can all learn from your awesome code) and we’ll spin up a dedicated <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/">Azure</a> instance running the appropriate stack.</li>
  <li><strong>Entries should be accessible.</strong> In line with the philosophy of progressive enhancement, your entry should be usable by the broadest number of users possible. <a href="http://www.accessiq.org/news/commentary/2012/09/web-accessibility-is-a-mindset-not-a-checklist">Accessibility is not a checklist</a>, but if you’re clueless about where to start, <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20-TECHS/">these techniques</a> can offer some guidance.</li>
  <li><strong>Nothing comes for free.</strong> In previous years, we gave a pass if you wanted to use jQuery or load some fonts from Typekit. This year we decided to change it up, not because we don’t love these products (we do), but because we wanted to force every piece of code, every asset, to fight for its place in your entry. Anything you add should be added with purpose.</li>
</ol>

<p>As with previous editions, your entry should use web standards and work in all modern browsers. You can use HTML, CSS, and JavaScript features and APIs that don’t have across-the-board support as long as you do so in keeping with the progressive enhancement philosophy. In other words, your entry can’t depend on that technology or feature in order to be usable.</p>

<p>All of this may sound like a tall order, but it’s entirely possible. In fact, the site we built for the contest also abides by these rules. My colleagues and I will touch on some of the techniques we used (and concessions we made) in building the site in future posts.</p>

<p>If you’ve read this far, you might be wondering <em>What’s in it for me?</em> Well, bragging rights, of course, but we’ve got some awesome prizes too! We’re giving away $10,000 to the top three entries, plus <a href="http://aneventapart.com/events">tickets to An Event Apart</a>, complete collections of <a href="https://abookapart.com/collections/standards-collection">A Book Apart titles</a>, and copies of <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/">my book</a> too. <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/#prizes">Complete details of the prizes</a> are over on <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/">the contest site</a>.</p>

<p>We’ve lined up an amazing group to judge the entires this year too: <a href="https://twitter.com/rachelandrew">Rachel Andrew</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/lara_hogan">Lara Hogan</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/wilto">Mat Marquis</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Heydonworks">Heydon Pickering</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/jensimmons">Jen Simmons</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/SaraSoueidan">Sara Soueidan</a> will all be putting your entry through its paces and peering under the hood at your code. There’s also a People’s Choice award which will be based on votes you cast. Voting will open October 1st and run through October 14th.</p>

<p>The contest opened Monday and we will accept entries until 5pm Pacific Time on September 30th. <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/legal">Everything you should need to know about the contest, eligibility, etc.</a> is up on <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/">the 10k Apart site</a>, but if you have additional questions, <a href="https://a-k-apart.com/hi">you can always reach out</a>.</p>

<p>I can’t wait to see what you come up with! Happy coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Should Pay 2: The Hosting]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/who-should-pay-2-the-hosting/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T08:39:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/who-should-pay-2-the-hosting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago, I argued that our <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/who-should-pay/">users should never foot the bill for developer convenience</a> and yesterday I stumbled on a post from EllisLab (the makers of ExpressionEngine) that echoes that sentiment, but from a different angle. The title might make you scratch your head: <a href="https://ellislab.com/blog/entry/save-thousands-of-dollars-by-paying-more-for-hosting">Save Thousands of Dollars by Paying More for Hosting</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>While it sounds counterintuitive, EllisLab’s statement makes sense. It’s all about shifting your perspective from agonizing over every hard cost on the balance sheet to thinking “big picture” about how you are spending your money overall.</p>

<p>Their post makes the case that a low-cost hosting may be cheaper on the surface, but its slow performance will end up costing you more in terms of productivity loss and/or actual billable hours. The comparison they use is modest, but with a big impact: GoDaddy at $59.88/year vs. Nexcess at $8.95/month (still inexpensive, but roughly 2x the cost).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Normally, the ExpressionEngine control panel is fast. Zippy even. There aren’t many pages in the control panel that should have an execution time of more than a second. Most pages take a fraction of a second, no fancy caching needed. It’s common to see this in the footer: “Script executed in 0.0706 seconds.” Sure, add-ons that are bad citizens can slow down the control panel, but typically not to the degree a bad host can.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>How about ten seconds per page? No joke, on a recent site we logged in to on GoDaddy, one of the faster pages in the Admin area took ten seconds. The Template Manager took fifteen seconds, the publish page twenty-plus. I felt terrible for the developer and client who were using this site daily. Not only were they having a terrible experience with our software, they were <em>losing money</em> and didn’t even know it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The post then proceeds to work through some estimations of normal workload in the CMS to determine how much money is quietly being drained from a project’s kitty because of a poor hosting decision. I won’t lie, it’s substantial.</p>

<p>Now the EllisLab post is focused more on agency and project costs, but the implications of a slow host extend to our end users too.</p>

<p>Sure, a slow host will delay the delivery of our content and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/01/technology/impatient-web-users-flee-slow-loading-sites.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">increase the likelihood they will go to a competitor</a>. That’s a given. But a slow host can also drain a mobile device’s battery (because the radio must be kept on longer), which reduces the usefulness of their device.</p>

<p>Slow servers are also incredibly frustrating for users and are inconsiderate of their time. This is one of the points I was harping on in my post: we should not value our time above our customers’ time. When we put our customers’ needs above our own, we make better products and (ultimately) better decisions for our businesses.</p>

<p>Long story short: Shop around for a good price on a speedy server. Your developers, content creators, and (most importantly) your customers will thank you for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Should Pay?]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/who-should-pay/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-18T23:35:06-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/who-should-pay</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In more than a handful of conversations lately, it’s become quite clear that we, the web development community, are prioritizing our own convenience and our own time over that of our users. With our industry’s focus on “user-centered design”, you might find that hard to believe, but it’s true.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Here’s one example. In reaction to <a href="/notebook/css-variables-are-a-bad-idea/">my post on why I think CSS variables are a bad idea</a>, <a href="http://sass-lang.com">SASS</a> core team member <a href="https://twitter.com/chriseppstein/">Chris Eppstein</a> had this to say:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/AaronGustafson">@AaronGustafson</a> Authoring CSS shouldn’t be so onerous as to require the use of a preprocessor.</p>&mdash; Chris Eppstein (@chriseppstein) <a href="https://twitter.com/chriseppstein/status/567756897105620992">February 17, 2015</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>Fundamentally, I agree with his sentiment: A preprocessor should <em>not</em> be a requirement for authoring CSS. Thankfully, <em>it never was</em>; you can build amazing things using only hand-authored CSS. And if you find a preprocessor helpful to your process for one reason or another, great. But using a preprocessor never has been (nor should it ever be) a requirement.</p>

<p>But Chris was not railing against preprocessors. Instead, he is echoing a sentiment held by many people in the preprocessor community. He feels CSS is not as powerful as it could/should be and he hopes that one day soon preprocessors won’t need to exist because CSS will have all of the features they offer natively. Like variables.</p>

<p>I used to feel that way. I used to want variables… and mixins… and functions… and loops… and declaration block-level inheritance. But I’ve changed my mind.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I love these constructs. I use them nearly every day in the SASS I write and I am incredibly thankful for the hard work that has gone into their creation and maintenance.  Chris alone has probably saved me several weeks worth of work over the last four years through his contributions to SASS and <a href="http://compass-style.org/">Compass</a>. I definitely owe him a beer (or three).</p>

<p>Ok, so if my issue is not with the idea of programmatically generating styles, why would I not want these to be part of CSS, the <i>lingua franca</i> for design on the Web? Well, it’s pretty simple: Converting all of these constructs into something that is actionable by the browser takes time and processing power. Someone has to pay that cost and I wouldn’t feel right passing that cost on to my end users if there are better options.</p>

<p>This is a topic I bring up often in my conference talks and workshops: Every decision we make affects the user experience in some way.</p>

<p>When we add another JavaScript library or plugin, it’s no big deal from our perspective. We tend to have fast connections and faster processors. For our users it’s another story: It’s one more thing to request. One more thing to download. One more script to parse. One more thing holding up page rendering. One more reason to leave our site and seek out a competitor who actually values their time.</p>

<p>When we hide an <code>img</code> in the small screen version of our responsive design using <code>display: none</code>, the cost to us is quite minimal. It’s just one little declaration. What’s the harm? But the cost to our end users is quite significant: Longer load times, slower performance, and (in some cases) in real dollars if they are on a <a href="http://blog.kaspersky.com/cost-aware/">metered data connection</a>. And they don’t even get to see the image they paid for!</p>

<p>When we decide to build a site using a front-end JavaScript MVC framework, it can make the development process go so much faster for us and we can reduce our need for a robust back-end infrastructure. I mean everyone has JavaScript these days… <a href="/notebook/a-fundamental-disconnect/">the browser is the new VM</a>. But when we do this, our users suffer because we don’t give their browsers real HTML. Instead we force them to download a hefty framework so we can move all of the processing we would normally handle on a much faster, dedicated server to their questionably-capable machine instead. Oh, and if the browser encounters an error while parsing or executing the JavaScript execution, they don’t get anything at all. Welcome to the Modern Web™!</p>

<hr />

<p>When I look around, I see our community spending a lot of time coming up with new tools and techniques to make our jobs easier. To ship faster. And it’s not that I’m against efficiency, but I think we need to consider the implications of our decisions. And if one of those implications is making our users suffer—or potentially suffer—in order to make our lives easier, I think we need to consider their needs above our own.</p>

<p>So yes, I would love a world where preprocessors are unnecessary, but I would much rather spend a few seconds (or even a few minutes) transcompiling my SASS into CSS in order to save my users even a few milliseconds. It’s the same reason I optimize my images, minify my JavaScript, use Gzip, and lazy load design and experience enhancements only in contexts where they provide a real benefit.</p>

<p>Our users should never foot the bill for our convenience. We need to put their needs above our own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
