<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Culture | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-15T18:07:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I’m Voting for Oscar]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/im-voting-for-oscar/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:06:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/im-voting-for-oscar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure id="fig-2016-10-11-1" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-11/oscar.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-11/oscar.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-11/oscar.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2016-10-11/oscar.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""></figure>

<p><a href="#fig-2016-10-11-1">This is my son Oscar</a>. In case you can’t see the picture, he looks nothing like me because he’s adopted. He’s also friggin’ adorable, but that’s not why I’m writing this. I’m writing this because my son is black and despite the fact that he will grow up in a family that has the means to provide him with a good education and far more opportunity than a lot of children in America—including me—the sheer fact that his skin is dark means he will grow up in a far different America than I did.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/shopping-while-black-americas-retailers-know-they-have-racial-profiling-problem-now-2222778">He will be suspected when he enters a store</a>. <a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/teachers/teaching_now/2016/03/bias.html">He will be treated differently in school</a>. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/11/us/heres-how-racial-bias-plays-out-in-policing.html">He will be policed differently</a>. If he commits a crime, he will be <a href="http://www.prisonpolicy.org/graphs/raceinc.html">six times more likely to be incarcerated</a> than his white friends in daycare; and if it’s a drug offense, he’ll be <a href="http://www.drugwarfacts.org/cms/Race_and_Prison">ten times more likely to serve time</a>.</p>

<p>He will be feared by default. He will be suspected by default. He will be guilty by default. All because he’s black.</p>

<p>I don’t want him to grow up in an America where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Philando_Castile">he could have his life ended during a traffic stop for a broken tail light</a>. I listened to Diamond Reynolds’ recording of Philando Castile dying and I had to stop the car and cry; I couldn’t bear to watch the video. He was someone else’s son. Someone else’s little boy.</p>

<p>This is not the America I want Oscar to grow up in and we have an opportunity to change it. I fully recognize that <a href="http://www.eisenhowerfoundation.org/docs/kerner.pdf">the societal issues that underly the way we (as a nation) treat the black community</a> and other people of color in the U.S. are not new, nor are they going to go away overnight. It’s going to take time and commitment to making it happen.</p>

<p>What I also know, however, is that electing a president who proposes <a href="http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2016/08/trumps-immigration-policies-follow-historical-racist-precedents/">racist policies</a>, uses <a href="http://www.azcentral.com/story/news/politics/onpolitics/2016/06/21/racist-comments-federal-judge-hurt-donald-trump-florida-ohio/86172262/">racist rhetoric</a>, and <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-paints-apocalyptic-picture-of-racial-tensions-in-u-s/">gins up racial tensions</a> among his supporters is not going to make America a safer place for Oscar to grow up. A man who <a href="http://www.sacbee.com/opinion/editorials/article99304487.html">routinely derides and demonizes immigrant populations</a> of varying shades (despite marrying numerous immigrants himself) is not going to lead us to be a more inclusive nation. And a man who has <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/24/opinion/sunday/is-donald-trump-a-racist.html">a history of treating the black community unfairly</a> is not going to be the champion we need to help unify our different racial and ethnic communities into that melting pot of ideas and cultures we’ve been taught is America’s greatest strength.</p>

<p>When I go to the polls this Fall to help my country choose its next leader, I will be thinking of my son and all of the other children in this great nation of ours. I will think about the future America they stand to inherit and I will vote against Donald Trump. I hope you will join me in taking a stand against fear, against further segregation of our society, and against racism. America is already great, and it will be much better without Trump.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Are Keys to Success?]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/what-are-keys-to-success/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-01T11:18:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/what-are-keys-to-success</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I got a message from someone I’ve been mentoring via email. His question was one I think a lot of folks in our industry struggle with:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Can you please tell what are keys to success and what should I do to become a successful programmer and software engineer? Anything is appreciated.</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<p>That’s a tough one. “Success” can be defined in so many ways. Is success making truckloads of money? Is it having 100,000 Twitter followers? Is it getting invited to speak at conferences in exotic locations? Those are very external notions of success, perhaps it’s more personal: Feeling like you’ve accomplished what you set out to do. Feeling like your life has meaning. Finding joy in both your work and your play. With so many ways to define success, there’s no magic formula for achieving it.</p>

<p>Unsure how to answer this perplexing question, I decided to answer by sharing what makes me feel successful—the Golden Rule. I used the Islamic version in my response:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>No one of you is a believer until he desires for his brother that which he desires for himself.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That I chose the Islamic version had more to do with where my protege resides than anything else. This concept is universal, cropping up in nearly every faith and philosophy as well as in numerous cultural proverbs:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Blessed is he who preferreth his brother before himself. (Baha’i)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>One should seek for others the happiness one desires for one’s self. (Buddhism)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do unto others as you would have them do unto you. (Chrisitianity)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Try your best to treat others as you would wish to be treated yourself and you will find that this is the shortest way to benevolence. (Confucianism)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>He sought for others the good he desired for himself. Let him pass on! (Egyptian)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t go around hurting people, and Try to understand things. (Hopi)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Humanists acknowledge human interdependence, the need for mutual respect and the kinship of all humanity. (Humanism)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In happiness and suffering, in joy and grief, we should regard all creatures as we regard our own self. (Jainism)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>One going to take a pointed stick to pinch a baby bird should first try it on himself to feel how it hurts. (Nigerian)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do as you would be done by. (Persian)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then there’s my personal favorite, from Judaism:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What is hateful to you, do not to your fellow man. That is the entire law; all the rest is commentary.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Golden Rule is a wonderful tool for helping maintain balance in your life, business, and relationships. And so, I followed this recommendation proverb with a bit more detail on how I feel we can embody this philosophy:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Treat others with respect (means respecting their time, dignity, etc.).</li>
  <li>Look for opportunities to help others accomplish <em>their</em> goals.</li>
  <li>Give of yourself freely without expecting return.</li>
</ul>

<p>My twelve years of Catholic schooling drummed the proverb “to whomever much is given, much will be required“ into my head, which accounts for my emphasis on sharing. I know that my “success”—as I define it at least—has been made possible by the generosity of others. And so I think it’s my duty to “<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0223897/">pay it forward</a>” and I look for every opportunity to create opportunities for others.</p>

<p>In my experience, living life this way—or at least improving on it a bit each day—makes me feel successful. Perhaps it will work for you as well.</p>

<p><em>Note: Passing along this tiny bit of wisdom made me feel successful today :-)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Don’t Want to Teach the World to Code… I Want to Teach the World to Problem Solve]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/i-dont-want-to-teach-the-world-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T17:51:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/i-dont-want-to-teach-the-world-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems that every other day a new code school opens it doors. In my mid-sized city, Chattanooga, there are no fewer than three businesses centered around teaching “coding” classes<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup> that I am aware of. And there are at least a half-dozen free or community driven programs and camps on top of that. Most are aimed at youth, but some offer adult education as well. And that, of course, is over and above what’s available in our public and private schools (which is considerable) and a plethora of online options.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>On one hand I think this is great. I love to code and I love to share my knowledge of that world with anyone who will listen (I’m sorry, Kelly). Also, as someone who ran a web design studio, I know first hand how hard it is to find talented people to hire. More coders equals a larger talent pool; it’s simple math.</p>

<p>Currently—at least here in the U.S.—the numbers aren’t where we need them to be. We just aren’t graduating enough STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) students. And the pressure to fill open positions has led to a lot of outsourcing and an increased demand for employment visas. As an unemployed or unhappy worker, making yourself employable as a coder sounds like a win-win.</p>

<p>Couple this with the constant barrage of news about startup acquisitions and funding rounds and it certainly seems like learning to code is your key to financial stability if not extreme wealth. (The “American Dream,” right?) But it’s not.</p>

<p>As Jerry Davis pointed out so deftly in the <cite>Harvard Business Review</cite>, <a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/2014/03/why-do-app-developers-still-live-with-their-moms/">the vast majority of startups don’t succeed</a>. Learning to code is not a guarantee of wealth and success. And, let’s be honest, not everyone is wired for coding and that’s okay.</p>

<p>So I’m not sure everyone needs to learn to code. That said, I think this movement (if you can call it that) has merit.</p>

<p>First off, on the Web side of things, I think learning to code can be empowering. The Web is for everyone and I love to see more and more people using it as a tool to amplify their voices and to build community across the globe. So for that reason alone I’m thrilled these programs exist.</p>

<p>The other reason I like that people are learning to code is that it changes how they see and deal with problems.</p>

<p>As a programmer, I am forced to break lumbering, gnarly problems into simpler, accomplishable tasks. I’m forced to think about cause and effect, of process, of the steps required to achieve the desired outcome.</p>

<p>I also experience failure. Constantly. I’ve learned to find the errors in my own logic, to second guess myself, to refine and improve, to refactor my code and my brain. This constant refinement helps me achieve a deeper understanding of my tools and my medium.</p>

<p>To me, those lessons (taught to me through nearly 20 years of coding) are invaluable. These are the sorts of lessons I wish they taught in school, but sadly the U.S. has largely done away with reason and critical thinking in favor of memorization and regurgitation. So maybe it’s something we need to learn at home. Or in a coding class.</p>

<p>Regardless, if the world was filled with curious people who asked questions, applied logic, and refined their understanding of the challenges they see every day, I can’t help but think we would all be far better off.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I should note that I am lumping a bunch of stuff into the umbrella of “coding” because some of these teach front-end web technologies, others teach those plus back-end stuff in PHP or Python, and others teach maker-style classes focused around robotics and DIY electronics like Arduino. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
